...
When I introduce lists, I said they were different from tuples
primarily because they're mutable.
I can change elements inside of that.
That's a really handy tool to have,
but it causes some really interesting potential
for problems.
And I want to show you where those can arise
and how you can guard against them.
So we're now going to talk about the idea of, not only mutation,
but of aliasing and of cloning, topics
that are really important, a little tricky to understand.
And again, go look at the Python tutor
if you want some help working through this after you've
listened to what we're about to discuss.
But let's think about this idea.
Again, I said that lists are mutable.
I can change them.
As a consequence-- it's not surprising-- they're
going to behave differently than immutable types.
In particular, what is a list?
It's an object in memory.
And I have a variable somewhere typically that's
going to point to that object.
That's how I refer to it.
That's how I say give me something
at a particular index.
One of the things about the list,
though, is I could have multiple variables pointing
to the same list.
These are now clones, if you like,
or copies-- actually, I'm going to say that differently.
They're not yet copies.
They are the same instance, but different names for them.
So they're really just aliases for that.
One of the things that could happen then
is that, if I go in and change an element of a list
under one name, it also changes under the version
as I reference it from the other name
because it points to the same place.
And that has some really potential for big side effects
that can cause interesting problems for us.
Let me give you an analogy.
I could have a famous person, and I could
associate attributes with them.
That person might also be known by many, different names.
So they could have nicknames.
And all of those nicknames point to the same person.
So for some of you, here's a famous person.
He's known as Justin Drew Bieber or as Justin Bieber
or as-- there's a whole bunch of nicknames for this young man.
And he also has some attributes associated with him.
He's a singer, and he's rich.
But if I add a new attribute to him,
something he's done recently, all of his nicknames
also refer to both the old attributes and the new ones.
So that the Bieb is not just a singer and rich,
he's also a troublemaker.
And J. Biebs is not just a singer
and rich, he's also a troublemaker,
all due respect to Mr. Bieber.
The point is that you share information
because you have aliases or nicknames
for the same structure.
Same problem, same issue, same opportunity
arises with the list.
So let's look at a couple of examples here.
I'm going to create a list-- and I'm
going to show you both on my computer
and separately-- of warm colors.
So I'm going to say, "This is a list
of red and yellow and orange."
And I'm going to say, "Hot is the same as warm."
In my global frame, I've actually created a binding,
where warm is bound to the list whose first element is
the string red, second element is yellow,
third element is orange.
Hot-- where does it point?
Oh, to the same place because notice what I did here.
I said, get the value of warm-- which is that arrow-- and bind
the name hot to the same place.
So it binds to that list.
And that says, as a consequence, two things.
One is if I print warm, I'm going to get that list.
If I print hot, I'm going to get that list.
But now, if I append something to hot, and I say,
"At the end of hot, add in a new hot color, pink."
What is hot?
It's that list.
But what is warm?
It's the same list.
And that's because I literally, in hot, added this element in,
and because warm points to the exact same structure,
it now has changed.
It has mutated.
And that's tricky because I might not
have intended to change warm but only hot since they were
pointing to the same thing.
One was an alias for the other.
I've had that indirect side effect that I wasn't expecting.
One of the consequences of this is that print is not the same
as a quality.
Strange statement.
But what it says is, even if two lists print out the same thing,
that does not mean they are the same structure.
And I can test that by mutating one and checking.
So again, let me type this in.
I'm going to give cool a set of colors-- blue, green, and gray.
And I'm going to define chill to also
be the set of cooler colors.
Notice this is different than what
I did in the previous case.
In the previous case, I said let hot equal warm.
Have it be the point of the same structure.
Here they point to different versions
of the same set of strings.
And you see that right here.
Cool is that list.
Chill is that list.
And while the names are the same,
they are different structures.
And so, in fact, if I look at cool-- I'm
going to do it more formally-- if I print out cool,
it prints that.
If I print out chill, looks the same, but they're not.
And here's how I can show it.
Because I can mutate them, I'm going
to change the second element of chill to be blue.
And now if I print cool, I still get blue, green, gray.
But if I print chill, I get blue, green, blue.
And that's important.
Because initially it might have looked
like they're the same thing.
They print the same.
They are not.
They point to different structures.
We have to be careful when we think about what we're
doing to test the quality, and we
have to be careful when we think about how we use elements
of structures that can mutate.
The third thing I can do is I can clone a list.
I can make a copy of it.
And so I can make a slight change
in what I did earlier on, which is that I could define cool,
again, to be this list of the cooler colors-- blue, green,
and gray.
And rather than copying the same set of strings over again,
I can simply say I want chill to be a clone of cool.
And again, notice the difference.
In the very first example, I said something
like let hot equal warm.
I could have said let chill equal cool.
But then chill would have pointed
to exactly the same list.
With that colon in there, I make a copy of chill.
And you can see that over here.
I've got cool pointing to one version.
I've got chill pointing to a second version.
And that now says, for example, if I mutate chill,
I append to it the color black.
And I print out chill.
Black is there, but cool has not changed.
And that makes sense because cool
is pointing to this structure.
I mutated or changed that structure.
Cloning lists is really useful when
I want to do something with a list that involves mutation,
but I don't want to, in fact, change the original list.
I can make a copy very quickly and use it.
And I'm going to show you an example of that
in just a second.
But we've seen aliasing and some of the effects of that
in terms of side effects.
We've seen cloning, and we've seen the fact
that because lists are mutable, I have to be careful
when I want to ask about are two things the same,
even if they print the same way.
We've already talked about this, but I want
to give you one more example.
I can sort a list, and I suggest that there
are two ways to do the sort.
I could use Sort, or I could use Sorted.
Sort mutates the list, changes the actual structure
but doesn't return anything.
Sorted doesn't mutate the list, essentially makes
a new version of the list in sorted order and returns that.
So I'm going to have to reassign that result to a variable.
And I've shown you an example here.
I started off with warm as a sequence of three colors.
I called Sort on it.
That's the method associated with warm.
And it will literally change the order of them.
And in fact, you can see over here,
after I've done that, warm is now
in a different order from where I started.
And so I have a different structure to that.
And in fact, warm now points to something different than what
I really originally began with.
Sorted warm has no value because Sort does not return anything.
If on the other hand, I set up cool as this list structure,
and I call Sorted on it-- which I do right there--
I'm going to return that to a variable name
because Sorted does not mutate the list.
Cool will not change in this case.
But what it will return is a new sorted list,
and I've now created a binding that points to that structure.
I'm sure somewhere along the line
you're going to use the wrong version of Sort of Sorted.
I do regularly.
It's OK.
But what you should see here is that if I
don't mind the mutation of the list, in fact, if I want it,
I can change it in place, using sort.
If I don't want to mutate the list,
I use Sorted, two useful tools to have associated with lists.
I can of course have, as I've already said,
arbitrary structures inside of lists.
So I could have nested lists, lists of lists.
They might be even lists of lists of lists.
One of the things that can happen here
is that I can still get side effects that
can occur after mutation.
And so let me show you an example of this.
I've defined warm to be the list of yellow and orange.
I've defined hot to be the list red.
So I've got warm.
I've got hot.
Then I'm going to set up bright colors to be a list of warm.
And there's the formation of it with the square braces.
And in fact, if I do it over here,
I'm going to set up warm to be the list of yellow and orange.
I said hot would be the list of red.
And bright colors is just a list of warm,
which is itself a list.
So there's the value of warm.
There's the value of hot.
And let's look at bright colors.
Oh, funky.
Two square braces.
The outer square braces say it's a list.
There's only one element in it.
And that element is itself a list that
has two things inside of it.
Now let's add something to bright colors.
I'm going to say, to bright colors, append at the end hot.
And I know what hot is it.
It is itself a list.
I created that earlier on.
And if I print out bright colors-- oh, very nice--
the outer square braces say it's a list.
And notice, I've got two elements inside of this.
The first one is a list that happens to be of two elements.
The second one is a list that happens to be of one element.
And you can see that here because bright colors
points to a list, each element of which itself
points to a list.
Now let's append, to hot, the color pink.
And if I do that-- I've already added it over here.
Let's see what happens if I print out hot.
Not surprisingly, it's a list of red and pink.
But notice the strange effect.
I didn't do anything here that directly used bright colors.
I didn't say do something to bright colors.
But if I print out bright colors, it's changed.
And it's changed, again, because of that aliasing or side
effect.
Because bright colors points to something,
one of whose elements points to a list,
when I change hot-- which I did-- I've also indirectly
changed bright colors.
And you can imagine this is occasionally
going to cause you some difficulties if you
change something you weren't expecting.
We'll see that having aliases can be valuable,
but we've already seen it could cause some side effects that I
wasn't expecting and could lead to computations
that aren't what I wanted.
Finally, if I print out the whole thing of hot plus warm,
I get, in this case, the nice concatenation of them.
But again, I haven't changed anything inside
of this structure.
And I remind you that's what we wanted, in some cases,
use concatenation because we want
to make a version of things that are glued together
rather than changing things in place.
And just to show you that.
If I go back and print hot, nothing has changed.
It's still red and pink.
One last topic about mutation, especially as
you come around to doing things around iteration.
If I'm going to iterate over a list,
I really want to avoid mutating that list as I iterate over it.
And here's a little piece of code
this intended to remove duplicates from two lists.
The idea is if I've got two lists,
I'd like to loop through the first list
and then go over the second list and say,
if I've already got a copy of that,
I'm going to remove it from the first list.
And I want to show you an example of this.
I'm going to just type in very quickly,
"Remove dupe of L1 and L2."
And it says, "4E and L1."
I'm going to say, "If it's already in L2,
I'm going to remove it from L1."
So there's a definition list.
As we've got on the slide, give it two examples.
I got one, two, three, four for L1,
and I have one, two, five, six, for L2.
And I do Remove Dupes of L1 from L2.
And I look at L1.
And it's two, three, four.
Wait a minute.
Why didn't I remove two?
Two also appears in L2 as well as in L1.
I should have removed it from L1, and I didn't.
Why?
And the answer is that Python, because it's
going over an iterable, uses an internal counter
to keep track of where it is inside the loop, what
element of the list is it going to be getting to next.
It's basically saying, how many times
have I gone through this loop.
When I mutate, which Remove does, when I mutate the list,
it changes the list, and it actually
caused Python to never see the element two.
Because it had gone through it the first time.
I've removed one.
I've mutated.
It's thinking, I'm going to look at the next element,
but I've changed the size of the list.
And the next element is no longer two.
It's now three.
So if I'm going to want to do something like this,
I have a tool.
I can't do that, but what I can do is make a copy.
And by making a copy, by cloning the list first, now
when I'm mutating L1, I've still got something
that I'm iterating over that hasn't
changed because it's pointing to a different structure.
Again, a place where you want to be
careful about accidentally causing problems
because of the mutation.
Just like in biology, mutation is not always a good thing.
Same thing in computer science or in Python.
It can be useful, but we ought to be careful about the side
effects that show up.