...
Just as strings come with standard operations in Python,
so do lists and tuples.
And I want to show you examples of standard operations
and lists that are really valuable to have.
The first one is, I could add something
to the end of the list.
And that's going to be nice as I want to accumulate results.
So let me show you a little example here.
I'm going to type in a definition for l as the list.
So a square race of 2, 1, and 3.
And just to make sure it's right,
I'm going to print out what l is, and there it is.
If I want to add something to the end of the list,
I can do that with append.
And there's a dot there that I'm going
to come back to in a second.
But I could append 5 to the end of the list.
It doesn't print anything, but it's done something for me.
And what's it done?
It's actually added 5 to the end of l.
So there is now the structure of it.
And the key issue here, is it has mutated it.
It has actually changed l itself.
So anything that was depending on l being three elements long
is now in trouble because it's now four elements long.
Now what about that funky little dot?
We've seen an example of this earlier,
we're going to see more of it later on.
This dot is taking advantage of something inside of Python.
Everything in Python, or almost everything in Python,
is an object.
And lists are an example of a Python object, a collection
of things put together.
Objects have data inside of them but they also
have methods and functions.
And we get to that by using that dot.
So, given an object name, for example, here it
was l, the dot says, get out some method.
Or if you want to think of it, some
function, associated with that kind of object.
And then call it, open print followed by close print.
And that's literally what's happening here,
is this dot is saying, look at l, what is it, it's a list.
So get the append method, or function, associated with lists
and apply it.
We'll come back to that later on but that's
what's happening when we use the append there.
Key point here is append can add something to a list.
Good thing to have.
We could also concatenate as we did with tuples or strings.
So if I've got one list, l1, and I've got another list,
l2, then I can add the two together.
So let me in fact do the same thing here.
I've got l1, let's call it again, the list 2, 1, 3.
I want to create l2, it's also going to be a list, 4, 5, 6.
And I can concatenate them.
I could say, let l3 be l1 plus l2.
And when I do that, I can look at l3.
And it's now the list of six things together.
Notice, by the way, that in this case,
l1 has not changed, nor has l2.
l3 is a new list that has been formed by concatenating
together copies of l1 and l2.
If I wanted to extend a list, I can
do that with an explicit call.
And extend basically does what you say, it says take a list
and add to the end of it.
And so I can do l1 and extend it, for example, with 0 and 6.
And now if I look at l1, it's changed, it mutated.
And that's the point.
So concatenation does not mutate, extension does.
And it makes sense.
Extension says you should take something and add to it,
as opposed to you should take something and do something
interesting with it, which is what concatenation does.
I can also remove things from lists.
I can delete an element at a specific point.
And I use that with just the general command+L for delete.
And I basically can do it by saying,
remove something from up to a particular place.
And I do it by giving it a specific element.
So let me take an example here.
Here is l1.
And if I do Del of l1-- and let's pick, I don't know,
the third element here-- now I look at l1, oh, good.
That element has disappeared.
I can also remove the element from the end
of a list, something that's very handy when
I'm trying to walk down a list.
And I do that with the pop method.
Comes from an old expression of popping something off
of a stack.
And it returns that actual element
as well as changing the list itself.
I can remove a specific element by using remove.
And what it will do is look for that actual element in the list
and remove it.
If that element occurs multiple times,
it's only going to remove the first occurrence,
and if you try and remove something not in the list,
it's going to give an error.
So for example, if I set up l to be this list,
2, 1, 3, 6, 3, 7, 0.
If I call l with remove of 2, it will
mutate the list, change the list,
taking that element out as you can see.
If I say remove 3, it will take the first instance of 3
out but it leaves the second one around,
as you can see right there.
If I delete a specific spot in the list,
I already did that, it takes out the next one in that list
at the first indice, which is right there.
And if I pop, it removes the last one
and returns it, again mutating the list.
So operations that I have on lists.
These are going to become handy as we start thinking
about doing things with lists.
I can go back and forth between lists and strings.
If I've got a string and I want to convert it into a list,
I can literally call the procedure or function, list,
on that string.
And it returns the list with every character
in the string now separated out as a separate element
of the list.
So let me show you a simple example.
I'm going to set list to be the string A, B, C. Not very
interesting but it will work.
And if I now say, give me the list of s,
it nicely gives me back a list with each character as
a separate string inside of that list.
I might want to do some processing on these lists
as well.
And so one of the things I can do
is I can use the split method to split a string
on a particular character.
If I call it just with a standard call on split,
it will do it on a particular character.
I can also split it on spaces if I give it no parameter.
And so I've got an example down here.
I've set up a string, s.
I can turn it into a list.
There it is.
I could also split the string and turn it into a list.
And that I've done by saying, I want
to split it at this character.
And notice what it's done.
It has literally broken it up into two parts.
There's the first part.
There's the second part right there.
I can also do conversions of lists back into strings.
So if I create a list such as this one here,
I can join them together using this call.
There's the join operation, there's the dot,
and I'm giving it an empty string.
And it's basically saying, given that this is a string,
use the join operation on that string
to merge everything together and it will return just the string
with the pieces stuck together.
If I want to, I can do a join but have
the join insert a character between each of the things.
And this case, I give it an underbar, I use the dot,
I ask it to join, and it returns the string with it
A underbar B underbar C.
And so I can go back and forth between lists and strings.
Again, something that's going to be
really handy in a little while.
There are a couple of other list operations of value.
I've already said, while I talk about a list
as being an ordered sequence, it doesn't
mean the elements inside have an order, but I can do that.
I could actually sort a list.
And I have two ways of doing the sorting.
I can sort the list and return a new version of it
or I could actually mutate the list and sort it itself.
And so I want to give you an example here.
If I set up l to be the list of 9, 6, 0, and 3,
it's certainly not sorted.
And if I look at l, there it is.
If I call the special function sorted on l,
it returns the sorted version of l.
But l itself has not changed.
That's handy if I want to keep l around but I
want a sorted version of it.
On the other hand, if I really don't
care about what I do with l afterwards
but I want the sorted version, I can call l.sort.
Again, some method with coming off after that
dot to tell me to do this.
I can do an open close to say invoke the function.
And now if I look at l, it is in fact sorted.
Similarly, I could reverse a list
by calling reverse as a method.
Using the dot to say use the reverse associated with lists,
and it will change l itself and create something
in reverse order.
Handy things to have.
Things that are going to let us start manipulating larger data
structures as we move forward with thinking
about how to do computation on bigger collections of pieces.
We can now bring all of these pieces
together because we've got loops, functions, range,
and lists.
And how do I want to bring them together?
We've already talked about range,
we said it was a special procedure.
And we said it returns something that behaves essentially
like a tuple.
Or if you want to think about it like a list,
but really more like a tuple.
It doesn't generate all of the elements at once, however.
Rather, it generates the first element
and provides a method that says, when you want the next one,
we'll give it to you.
That's nice if I don't want to have
to generate a huge range before I start doing some computation.
But I can think of ranges now as acting like a tuple.
So a range of 5 really behaves like the tuple 0 through 4.
Or if you want to think of it that way,
like the list 0 through 4.
Range of 2, 6 is going to behave as
if it was that collection of those integers, as a tuple
or as a list.
And as a consequence, when we use range
in a for loop, what that loop variable is doing
is just iterating over that range as if it were a list.
We could write it directly, but it's
going to be a nice convenient shortcut to have because we're
going to be able to do things much more
efficiently without generating the entire range
before we start working on it.